<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Business Intelligence | Jon Mead]]></title>
  <link href="http://jonmead.me/blog/categories/business-intelligence/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jonmead.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-19T07:51:27+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jonmead.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jon Mead]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Changing World of Business Intelligence]]></title>
    <link href="http://jonmead.me/2013/01/24/the-changing-world-of-business-intelligence/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-24T22:12:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jonmead.me/2013/01/24/the-changing-world-of-business-intelligence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have spent the first half of this week in an internal <a href="http://www.rittmanmead.com">Rittman Mead</a> sales workshop, during which there have been a lot of discussions about the past and future of Business Intelligence, or <a href="http://www.oracle.com/us/solutions/business-analytics/overview/" title="Oracle Business Analytics - Overview | Solutions | Oracle">Business Analytics</a> as <a href="http://www.oracle.com">Oracle</a> are now calling it.</p>

<p>One thing that struck me was the change in Business Intelligence compared to when I started working in the industry.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There used to be a fairly straight forward graphic that was used to explain Business Intelligence.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/299238/2013-01-23_22-31-32.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The bottom of the pyramid was the data in the organisation, there was then a transformation layer that turned it into information, it was then consumed by end users as knowledge which could be used in their decision making process.</p>

<p>I feel this has now been replaced by the following graphic.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/299238/2013-01-23_22-33-58.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>This model still starts with data, however the source, volume, variety and velocity (deliberately borrowed from standard <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Data" title="Big Data">Big Data</a> definitions) of this data has increased. The organisation now looks at more internal sources of data, plus external sources of data as well, such as social media and third party market research.</p>

<p>The biggest change is the transformation layer. Depending on the source of data and the questions that are being asked of the organisation there are now two differ approaches: schema on write and schema on read.</p>

<h3>Schema on Write</h3>

<p>This is the traditional approach for Business Intelligence. A model, often dimensional, is built as part of the design process. This model is an abstraction of the complexity of the underlying systems, put in business terms. The purpose of the model is to allow the business users to interrogate the date in a way they understand.</p>

<p>The model is instantiated through physical database tables and the date is loaded through an ETL (extract, transform and load) process that takes data from one or more source systems and transforms it to fit the model, then loads it into the model.</p>

<p>The key thing is that the model is determined before the data is finally written and the users are very much guided or driven by the model in how they query the data and what results they can get from the system. The designer must anticipate the queries and requests in advance of the user asking the questions.</p>

<h3>Schema on Read</h3>

<p>Schema on read implies works on a different principle and is more common in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Data" title="Big Data">Big Data</a> world. The data is not transformed in any way when it is stored, the data store acts as a big bucket.</p>

<p>The modelling of the data only occurs when the data is read. Map/Reduce is the clearest example, the mapping is the understanding of the data structure. <a href="http://hadoop.apache.org/" title="Welcome to Apache™ Hadoop®!">Hadoop</a> is a large distributed file system, which is very good at storing large volumes of data, this is potential. It is only the mapping of this data that provides value, this is done when the data is read, not written.</p>

<h3>New World Order</h3>

<p>So whereas Business Intelligence used to always be driven by the model, the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extract,_transform,_load" title="ETL">ETL</a> process to populate the model and the reporting tool to query the model, there is now an approach where the data is collected its raw form, and advanced statistical or analytical tools are used to interrogate the data. An example of one such tool is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R_(programming_language)" title="R">R</a>.</p>

<p>The driver for which approach to use is often driven by what the user wants to find out. If the question is clearly formed and the sources of data that are required to answer it well understood, for example how many units of a product have we sold, then the traditional schema on write approach is best.</p>

<p>If the question is more open, for example what is causing our sales of a product to drop, why are customers churning or even <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_are_known_knowns" title="There are known knowns - Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia">unknown unknowns</a>, then the schema on read is most appropriate.</p>

<h3>Decisions, Decisions, Decisions</h3>

<p>Whichever approach is taken the end result is that the user, or business, wants to make a decision, or take some action based on making sense of some data. Organisations are becoming increasingly data driven, and despite the evolution of Business Intelligence, the ability of an organisation to derive value from data will be key to its success.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Decision Making]]></title>
    <link href="http://jonmead.me/2013/01/20/decision-making/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-20T09:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jonmead.me/2013/01/20/decision-making</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Business Intelligence is designed and implemented to enable managers to make better business decisions. Business Intelligence provides metrics or numbers that reflect the organisation's performance. At a high level this could be more profit, reduced costs or confirmation of adherence to laws, however does this reach as far as game changing strategies?</p>

<p>Part of the reason I am interested in this is because the value an organisation gets from Business Intelligence determines how much they will invest in it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The question I have is how useful it is at doing this, this question is borne partly from my experiences of implementing Business Intelligence systems for a number of clients, and partly from my own experiences of running Rittman Mead. The key definition for me is what are the key decisions that define businesses and what are the day to day decisions that sustain businesses.</p>

<p>I would suggest that decisions that define businesses, for example, that take them into a new market, start producing a new product are made using acumen, experience and intuition. These are human traits, not something derived from numbers. Decisions that sustain the business are much more effectively made by using metrics.</p>

<p>Examples of sustaining a business for me, I and based on our experiences at Rittman Mead would be looking at project profitability, staff utilisation, cash flow and overall profit and loss. We have very detailed metrics for these items. If any of them fall too far from target, the company could be in serious trouble, so maintaining these is essential to maintaining the company. Business Intelligence is key here and we use tables, graphs and dashboards to view this data.</p>

<p>For more strategic decisions, such as opening an office in the US or India, or purchasing an <a href="http://www.oracle.com/us/solutions/ent-performance-bi/business-intelligence/exalytics-bi-machine/overview/" title="Oracle Exalytics In-Memory Machine">Exalytics</a> server then it comes back to a human decision, with the current tools we use there is no way we can prove this is going to be a ground breaking decision, or a ruinous one. What we can to is plan for the impact it has, we can see if we have the cash reserves to do it, and we can measure what the impact will be by doing it by measuring pipeline, sales, revenue and costs against their current values.</p>

<p>Books such as <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Competing-Analytics-New-Science-Winning/dp/1422103323" title="Competing on Analytics: The New Science of Winning - Amazon.co.uk">Competing on Analytics</a> argue that some organisations get ahead by using analytics (read numbers, business intelligence etc), i would argue that often in the examples analytics is used to support and enhance strategies, not define them.</p>

<p>Therefore in order to understand how to run a business successfully a manager must understand their own psychology of decision making, and potentially the industry or market they are in.</p>

<p>So to understand how to make a company great do we need to understand how humans make decisions better, for example looking at various biases and heuristics we follow, or do we have to get better Business Intelligence or analytics systems.</p>

<p>For me the answer is both, people have to come up with strategies and then use Business Intelligence to prove they are sustainable.</p>

<p>One footnote I would like to add to this is Big Data. Where Big Data can potentially change this paradigm, Big Data and it's exploration allows organisations to potentially find out new information which they were unaware of, which could then become the seeds for future strategies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting OEID up and running]]></title>
    <link href="http://jonmead.me/2013/01/19/getting-oeid-up-and-running/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-19T16:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jonmead.me/2013/01/19/getting-oeid-up-and-running</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Create the project</h3>

<p>Create new Integrator project</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/299238/2013-01-18_23-01-04.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Create OEID data store</p>

<p>Copy the <code>workspace.prm</code> file from the quickstart application. Edit the <code>workspace.prm</code> file. Change the parameter <code>DATA_STORE_NAME</code>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Create the data store</h3>

<p>Create a new graph called InitDataStore. Copy one component that contains the web service call to create a data store. Just copy the <strong>Create Data Store</strong> component.</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/299238/2013-01-18_23-11-43.png" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Run the graph</h3>

<p>Use the run button. Test by pinging the URL <a href="http://localhost:7770/admin/data-store-name?op=ping">http://localhost:7770/admin/data-store-name?op=ping</a> (Note: 7770 is the default port the Endeca Server runs on).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
